Okay, so in this video I'm gonna talk
to you about classes and what we can do
with them or in this case, we're actually
gonna create an object from a class.
So let's, uh, get started on this right away.
So first of all, I'm gonna create a class
object so let's, uh, start with new Java
class, I'm gonna call this class Dog.
Now my Dog class is gonna have some attributes
now, normally at this stage, I would just
tell you to create a main method we don't
need to do that when we're creating objects.
So let's get straight into
creating the Dog objects.
So first of all, let's give it a name, so we used
string name so just like before, when we were
creating objects, I might say string name equals
fido and that would create a name but we're gonna
do, use this method to create multiple Dogs.
So string name, we're gonna have an integer,
which is gonna be the age of the Dog okay?
So we're gonna use in age and finally we're
gonna use breed so we'll go back to string
and have a breed for our Dog, so there you go.
Now creating the attributes isn't enough.
We need to be able to create an object
from that or construct an object.
In order to do that, we're gonna need a
constructor, so by using alt and insert,
I'm able to bring up the Generate menu.
You can do that also by using the right
mouse click so let me just show you that.
So if I go to write Mouse click, it's generate
down and what I want to do is I want to create
a constructor, so I'm gonna do that now.
I just highlight the three attributes
I'm using and click okay and what that
does is that creates the constructor.
This allows us to create the object.
Now our constructor has got the name, the
age, and the breed, and that's being passed
in to this method using the parenthesis.
You can see them here and here, the brackets,
so the string name, the end age and the string
breed and what's happening is the name that's
coming from here becomes the object's name.
So when you think about the word
this, it's referring to the object
that we're actually creating.
So this name will equal name, so whatever
the name is, we'll pass into there.
The age will appear here, and it'll pass into the
age of the object, and the breed, which is over
here, will pass into the breed of the object.
So it's actually quite simple
when creating your constructor.
So let's create the object itself.
So I'm gonna do that in another class so
what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna create a
new class, and I'm gonna call it program.
Program is where we're gonna run the appliCation.
So inside of program, I am going to need a
main method so let's create that straight away.
So I'm just gonna type in main like we've done
before, press ,return, and that brings up the main
method, and what I'll do is I'll create an Dog.
So we're gonna create an instance of the Dog and
we're gonna use, use the Dog class to do this.
So what I need to do is put in Dog now you'll
see as soon as I've typed in capital D, we have
the first object Dog with a default package.
That's because Dog has been created inside
this program or inside this project.
So let's do that.
Now like any attribute, we need to create
a name for our object, so in this case I'm
gonna create D one, so D one is gonna be the
first instance of Dog and I need to set it up.
So we're gonna set it up as a new Dog and
we're gonna have to give it some values.
Now you'll see just above my brackets, I've got
string name in age, string breed, just to remind
me the order in which I type the information in.
So we'll go for Fido.
We will give it an age of six and we'll
say the breed is Border Collie like so.
Okay and what I'll also do
is we'll create a second Dog.
So let's call that one D two, and D two is
also gonna be a new Dog, new Dog, like so and
this one is gonna be called Scooby, and Scooby
is gonna be 10 and Scooby is a Great Dane.
It is important to create your class
before you try creating the objects.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna create
a Cat object, so I'm just gonna go Cat
well look, Cat isn't giving me an option
here, and if I press space, it'll go
red to indicate that it's not happy.
So let's get rid of that.
So in order for me to create a Cat class, I need
to go back over to here and start a new class.
So let's just do that, I'll call it Cat.
And in the case of the Cat class,
we're gonna give it a name.
We're gonna give it an age.
And we'll give it a breed as well.
So string breed, and actually I've
just noticed I've made a mistake there.
So let's go up to string.
Capital S must be very important to make
sure you've got it typed in correctly.
So let's create.
Our Cat now.
So they'll go back to our program and create a Cat
where you'll see that Cat is now available as part
of the default package, and I'll create a Cat.
So C1.
Now it's happy at the moment, but if I try
to create a new instance of the Cat and use
the brackets, you can see that we've got no
parameters set up, so I need to go back to
our Cat and I need to set up that constructor.
So if you create an object without a
constructor, you may run into some problems.
So let's just create that constructor.
If you remember, I'm gonna use alt an insert hit.
constructor, highlight the three attributes
and click okay, and there you go we've got it.
There's nothing stopping you from typing
this information in, but I find it's
a lot easier if you do it this way.
One of the other things I will bring to your
attention when it comes to creating a constructor
though, is that the constructor name must be the
same as the class name, so we've got a constructor
called Cat and we've also got a class called Cat.
I'm gonna create a second constructor for our Cat
and we are going to just leave this one blank.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm just gonna go
public Cat, and it's just gonna be blank
like so, and I'm gonna say, uh, this dot name
equals no name, this dot age equals, well, we
can't put no age because it's, uh, an integer
so I'm just gonna set the value to zero
and this dot breed equals no breed.
We'll go back to our program and as you
can see now, it's happy, and that's because
I've created a default instance of the Cat.
Okay, so let's just show you what I
can actually do with these objects.
So if I wanted to print out the Dog's name, so
let's just choose which Dog so I'll go for D
one.name and then run this like, so you'll see at
the bottom of the screen it'll say Fido so it's
happy with that, so it's picked out the name Fido.
So what I've done is I have put in the
instance of the object, which is D one,
and I've asked for it to display the name.
If I was to do that with the second Dog,
I can go to D two like so, and if I run
that, I should get Scooby, there you go.
Now if I try and do that with the Cat now,
bearing in mind that I've not actually
entered any information about the Cat,
let's just run that and see what happens.
And there you go, it says no name
because it's taken it from that
constructor that I created earlier.
Well, let's create a second instance of a Cat.
I'm gonna do Cat C2 equals new Cat.
Only this time I'm gonna give it a name.
So we'll call it Felix, and we're gonna give Felix
now, can you notice as soon as I typed in the
name, it's gonna start using that constructor.
So we'll give Felix an age of four
and we'll say that Felix is a tabby.
Now if I come back down to here, and
change it to C2 and run it, you'll
see that the name Felix appears.
I hope you enjoyed that and I look
forward to you seeing more of my videos.